Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office. Research Department Records, 1923-1986 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office. Research Department records 1923-1986 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office
6.94 linear feet Extent: 5205 Items
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. The Research Department was responsible for undertaking market research projects and disseminating research information, primarily for JWT's New York Office. The Research Department Records contain market research reports and other studies conducted for JWT. Includes some reports outsourced to a research firm, ASI Market Research, Inc. Research reports include television commercial studies; consumer opinion polls; product-specific studies; and market demographic reports including small town/rural markets; newspaper and magazine circulation; and African American consumer behavior. Clients represented include Chesebrough-Pond's, Coca-Cola, Kodak, Ford, Kellogg's, Kraft, and Rustenburg Platinum Mines. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
RL.00735
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, certain original reports are closed to researchers for preservation concerns. Use Copies are available in collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office. Research Department Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts in 1987 and 1993.
Historical Note
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. The Research Department was responsible for undertaking market research projects and disseminating research information, primarily for JWT's New York Office.
Collection Overview
The Research Department Records contain market research reports and other studies conducted for JWT. Includes some reports outsourced to a research firm, ASI Market Research, Inc. Research reports include television commercial studies; consumer opinion polls; product-specific studies; and market demographic reports including small town/rural markets; newspaper and magazine circulation; and African-American consumer behavior. Clients represented include Chesebrough-Pond's, Coca-Cola, Kodak, Ford, Kellogg's, Kraft, and Rustenburg Platinum Mines.
Collection Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into three series: the Account Files Series, the Reports Series, and the Oversize Materials Series. The Account Files Series contains market research reports and other studies conducted for specific JWT clients. The Reports Series contains reports and market research presentations not associated with a specific client. The Oversize Materials Series includes client-specific reports removed from the Account Files Series.
Subject Headings
J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; Chesebrough-Pond's.; Coca-Cola Company; Eastman Kodak Company; Ford Motor Company; Kellogg Company; Kraft Foods Company; Warner-Lambert Company; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- History; Advertising agencies -- United States; African American consumers; Consumer behavior -- United States; Demographic surveys -- United States; Marketing research -- United States; American newspapers -- Circulation -- United States; Television commercials -- United States; Reports; Photographs; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives:
Advertising and Marketing Intelligence Database Records
Advertising Vertical Files
Marketing Vertical Files
Chicago Office Non-Proprietary Research Reports
Detroit Office Goldfarb Consultants Ford Research Reports
Eleanor Newman Papers
Thomas Sutton Papers
Contents of Collection
- Account files, 1973-circa 1986 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Contains market research reports and other studies conducted for specific JWT clients. Includes television commercial studies for several clients, with breakdowns of age, income, viewing habits and product preferences among television commercial viewers from the 1980s. Also includes short reports of consumer opinion on particular products, including the Pond's Your Skin 'Dies' A Little campaign. Original folder titles were maintained and items were arranged alphabetically. Television commercial studies are organized by commercial format.
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield (Box 1)
    - Strategic Study on Health Prepayment
      - Executive Summary, 1974 (Box 1)
      - Insurance, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Diet Coke, television commercial studies, circa 1986
    - 15-second format, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - 30-second format (Box 1)
    - Computer tabulations (Box 1)
  - Ford Tempo, television commercial studies, circa 1986
    - 15-second format, (1-5 of 7 folders) (Box 1)
    - 15-second format (continued), (6-7 of 7 folders) (Box 2)
    - Computer tabulations, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Kellogg's Bran Flakes, television commercial studies, circa 1986
    - 30-second format (Box 2)
    - Unidentified format (Box 2)
      [Some items removed to Oversize Materials]
    - Computer tabulations (Box 2)
  - Kodak
    - Communications Plan, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Instant Cameras Communications Study, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire, undated (Box 2)
    - Television commercial studies, circa 1986 (Box 3)
      - 15-second format, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      - 30-second format, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Unidentified format (Box 3)
      - Computer tabulations (Box 3)
  - [Kraft, television commercial studies, circa 1986: removed to Oversize Materials] (Box 3)
  - Listerine, television commercial studies, circa 1986
    - Unidentified format, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Computer tabulations (Box 3)
  - Pond's, interviews for Your Skin 'Dies' a Little Campaign, undated (Box 3)
  - Rustenburg Platinum Mines, Ltd.
    - Report on American Jewelers' Attitudes and Habits, 1977 May (Box 3)
    - Study of the American Consumer Market for Platinum, 1977 Nov. (Box 3)
- Reports, 1923-1986 and undated, (4 boxes)
  Series contains reports and market research presentations not associated with a specific client. Some reports from the 1920s and 1930s account for lifestyles in rural markets in New York and Indiana. Series also includes television commercial studies performed by ASI Market Research, Inc. detailing viewers' demographic information, viewing habits and product preferences in several regions in California and the Midwest. Items are divided into Open Files and Restricted Files subseries, and arranged alphabetically by title.
  Restriction on Access: Originals of certain reports have been closed to researchers for preservation concerns. Use Copies are available in the collection.
  - Open Files
    Subseries includes Use Copies of materials held in the Restricted Files subseries.
    - Analysis of Retail Grocery Sales by Type of Outlet [Use Copy], 1936 (Box 3)
    - Analysis of the Subscription Circulation of 44 Magazines in Metropolitan Cincinnati [Use Copy], 1923, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Analysis of the Subscription Circulation of 44 Magazines in Metropolitan Cincinnati [Use Copy], 1923 (continued), (2 of 2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Area Distribution of Drug and Grocery Outlets, Utica, NY [Use Copy], 1924 (Box 4)
    - Can We Sell a Manufacturing Combine Our Idea of Centralizing Advertising Control? [Use Copy], 1929 (Box 4)
    - Cigarettes: Their Role and Function, A Study for the Chicago Tribune, undated (Box 4)
    - Consumer Behavior Group Presentation, undated (Box 4)
    - Continuous Contact with the Trade--Reactions from Dealer, Jobber and Chain Store [Use Copy], 1924 (Box 4)
    - Economic Conditions that Have Forced Us Out of a 'Seller's Market' to a 'Buyer's Market' [Use Copy], 1924 (Box 4)
    - Evolution and Function, Department of Information and Records [Use Copy], 1923-1938 (Box 4)
    - Finger-Tip Touch with Ever-Changing Market Conditions [Use Copy], 1924 (Box 4)
    - Future of the American Family, undated (Box 4)
    - Magazine Circulation Distribution and Coverage by JWT Market Classification [Use Copy], circa 1954 (Box 4)
    - Mock Readership Survey, 1956 June (Box 4)
    - Negro Market
      - Negro Lifestyle, 1962 (Box 4)
      - Negroes and Media, 1962 (Box 4)
      - Negro Attitudes Toward Food, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Newspapers in Utica, NY [Use Copy], 1924 (Box 4)
    - Preliminary Beer Study, 1954 Jul. (Box 4)
    - Preliminary Comparison of Price Policies of Clients [Use Copy], 1926 (Box 4)
    - Research Conference, 1975 Oct. 16 (Box 4)
    - Research Conference, 1977 Nov. 10, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Research Conference, 1977 Nov. 10 (continued), (2 of 2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Research and Planning: A Research Seminar Reference Book, 1982, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Role of Research in the Advertising Development Process, 1979 Apr. 10 (Box 5)
    - Rural and Small Town Investigation, Putnam County, NY [Use Copy], 1923 (Box 5)
    - Rural and Small Town Investigation, Randolph County, IN [Use Copy], 1924, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Small Town and Rural Investigation Among Subscribers to People's Home Journal [Use Copy], 1925, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Study of Public Attutides Toward Financing the Public Schools, 1974 June (Box 6)
    - Summary of Findings on Report of Investigation into the Market for Hair Tonics, 1937 (Box 6)
    - Syndicated Advertising Research Services, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Utica: City of Opportunity [Use Copy], 1923 (Box 6)
    - Visualization of Crossley Nationwide Survey of Beer and Ale Consumption, 1954 (Box 6)
    - 15-Second Commercial Project, 1986, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Restricted Materials
    Subseries contains original reports from the 1920s-1930s. Includes some photographs of small towns, townspeople and farmers in New York and Indiana.
    Restrictions on access: originals restricted for preservation purposes. Use Copies available in collection.
    - Analysis of Retail Grocery Sales by Type of Outlet, 1936 (Box 7)
    - Analysis of the Subscription Circulation of 44 Magazines in Metropolitan Cincinnati, 1923, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Area Distribution of Drug and Grocery Outlets, Utica, NY, 1924 (Box 7)
    - Can We Sell a Manufacturing Combine Our Idea of Centralizing Advertising Control?, 1929 (Box 7)
    - Continuous Contact with the Trade--Reactions from Dealer, Jobber and Chain Store, 1924 (Box 7)
    - Economic Conditions that Have Forced Us Out of a 'Seller's Market' to a 'Buyer's Market,' 1924 (Box 7)
    - Evolution and Function, Department of Information and Records, 1923-1938 (Box 7)
    - Finger-Tip Touch with Ever-Changing Market Conditions, 1924 (Box 7)
    - Magazine Circulation Distribution and Coverage by JWT Market Classification, circa 1954 (Box 7)
    - Newspapers in Utica, NY, 1924 (Box 7)
    - Preliminary Comparison of Price Policies of Clients, 1926 (Box 7)
    - Rural and Small Town Investigation, Putnam County, NY, 1923 (Box 7)
    - Rural and Small Town Investigation, Randolph County, IN, 1924, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Small Town and Rural Investigation Among Subscribers to People's Home Journal, 1925, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Small Town and Rural Investigation Among Subscribers to People's Home Journal,1925, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Utica: City of Opportunity, 1923 (Box 7)
- Oversize Materials, circa 1986, (3 boxes)
  Series contains television commercial reports removed from Account Files Series. Items arranged alphabetically by client.
  - Account Files (Box 8)
    - Kellogg's, television commercial studies, circa 1986, (1-3 of 6 folders) (Box 8)
    - Kellogg's, television commercial studies, circa 1986 (continued), (4-6 of 6 folders) (Box 9)
    - Kodak, television commercial studies, circa 1986 (Box 9)
    - Kraft, television commercial studies, circa 1986 (Box 9)